#### CHANDRASHEKHAR (CHANDRA) GOVIND RANADE

10518 Rosehaven St., Apt#414, Fairfax, VA22030

I have a long experience in teaching economics, statistics and mathematics, and in doing economic analysis. My teaching experience includes diverse students from the US high schools to colleges and universities, graduate students as well as key policy makers from several developing and emerging markets economies. I have taught and worked under both well-disciplined environment, and not so well-disciplined environment. The breadth and depth of my experience and expertise helps me in creating excellent learning environment in my classroom as well as with people I interact.

Competing the Online Data Analytics Bootcamp offered by the George Washington University in the middle of February 2022.

#### **EDUCATION:**

Education leading to university degrees:

Johns Hopkins University (Degree 2005)

2002-2004

Master of Arts in Education leading towards the Certified Mathematics Teacher.

Cornell University (Degree 1977)

1972-1976

*Ph.D.* in Economics with specialization in agricultural economics This involved numerous applications of mathematics and statistics.

Indian Statistical Institute (Degree 1969)

1966-1969

Master of Statistics

(specialization in Econometrics&Planning)

B.Sc. in Statistics, Mathematics and Physics

University of Pune (Degree 1966)

1962-1966

Other Key Training Program:

Various training workshops on Online teaching using Moodle Platform Organized at Stratford University.

2011 and 2012

Critical Thinking in Education
Organized by Stratford University
Dec. 2009
(Based on the Foundation for Critical Thinking, Berkley, CA)

**Workshop in AP Statistics** (Organized by College Board)

**June 2006** 

Workshop in AP Calculus AB (Organized by College Board)

August 2005

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Member of India Agriculture Group Based in Washington DC

5/2012 till present

India Agriculture Group is an informal group of retired World Bank professionals from India

Faculty Member, Semester at Sea Spring 2016, Global Voyage

1/2/ 2016 4/15/2016

This voyage was organized by the Institute of Shipping Education, Charlottseville. The voyage was sponsored by the University of Virginia. I taught 3 courses on International Finance, Development Economics and International Trade I organized field trips in the countries visited. Over a period of 110 days we travelled by ship and visited 12 countries.

# Faculty Member, Semester at Sea Spring 2014, Global Voyage

1/7/ 2014 5/2/2014

This voyage was organized by the Institute of Shipping Education, Charlottseville. The voyage was sponsored by the University of Virginia. I taught 2 courses on Development Economics and International Trade There were 80 students the Devlopment Economics course and 30 students in the International Trade course. I organized field trips in the countries visited. Over a period of 110 days we travelled by ship and visited 12 countries.

#### Full Time and Adjunct Professor at Stratford University

6/2008 till **Present** 

I have been teaching Basic Mathematics, Statistics and Algebra. In addition I have been teaching Research Methods, Statistics, International Finance, Economics for MBA students.

# Adjunct Professor at University of Bridgeport

8/2014 till

**Present** 

I have been teaching online courses in Finance, Statistics and Economics

#### Adjunct Professor at the Virginia International University 9/2007 to 12/2014

I have taught the following courses here: International Trade, Enterprise Resource Planning, Long Term Financial Decisions, Applied Statistics for Management Science and Marketing Research for the second year MBA students.

# Faculty Member, Semester at Sea Spring 2012, Global Voyage

1/16/ 2012 5/2/2012

This voyage was organized by the Institute of Shipping Education, Charlottseville. The voyage was sponsored by the University of Virginia. I taught 3 courses on Development Economics, International Trade and Global Finance. There were 30 students in each of these courses. I organized field trips in the countries visited. Over a period of 4 months we travelled by ship and visited 12 countries.

#### **Upper School Math Teacher**

2/2003 to 6/2009

Teach AP Calculus, AP Stat and Pre-Calculus I also teach AP Micro-economics in the coming year. I have been an advisor to students.

During this period I taught full time for 3 years at Wakefield School, The Plains, VA, from 2005-2008. Also, I taught full time for Spring Semester in Macgruder School located in Rockville, Md.; National Cathedral School located in Washington DC and The Madeira School located in McLean Virginia. I also did tutoring at the Sylvan Learning Centre located in Gaithersburg, Md.

#### **University of Rhode Island**

Fall 2001 to December 2002

Kingston, Rhode Island

At URI I was working as a Visiting Faculty Member. In the last academic year I taught two a courses, namely, Economics of Environmental Resource Management and Policy in the Fall Semester, and Trade and Environment in the Spring Semester. In the first year during the Fall Semester I have been teaching a course called Social Cost Benefit Analysis Course. I have also been doing policy analysis work with John Mellor, Vice President of Abt Associates on Development Economics and has co-authored two papers with him on Egypt and Rwanda entitled, "Modeling Egyptian Employment With a Three Sector Model—Agriculture, Non-tradables, and Urban Tradable"

The World Bank 1985 till March 2000

Washington, D.C. Senior Agricultural Economist

Until I took early retirement from the World Bank, I have appraised and supervised several projects. I have also prepared several sector reports. These sector reports as well as projects include environmental analysis. Apart from living and working in India,

where I was born, I have lived and worked in the Philippines and Ghana. In the World Bank Institute, I was managing training programs on Rural Project Analysis in the Transition Economies of the Former Soviet Union countries, Cambodia and Vietnam; and Policy Analysis programs in the South Asia, Central Asia, and the Middle East and North Africa Region. The training programs included topics from Sustainable Agriculture to Environmental Action Impact Matrix, Water Policy Analysis and Land Economics.

The World Bank also gave me an opportunity to learn several skills in the Information Technology Sector such as Web Development. I have completed a full certificate level course from the Learning Tree International on Java Programming and can now develop my own multimedia web page.

#### **International Food Policy Research Institute**

1983-1985

Washington, D.C.

Research Scholar

Worked on the issues related to land and labor productivity in Africa and came to the World Bank on secondment to work on a research project called, "Managing Agricultural Development in Africa" in DEC.

### **Indian Institute of Management**

1977-1983

Ahmedabad, India Professor

Taught graduate level courses, and managed and taught in the Management Development Programs courses such as Managerial Economics, Macroeconomics and Rural Development. I did extensive research on Rural Cooperatives, both commodity-specific as well as multi-purpose. I also worked as a consultant to the Government of India, various private companies, The World Bank and FAO. Particularly notable assignments include the evaluation of Integrated Cotton Development Project (financed by The World Bank), Rural Cooperatives in India, Agriculture AT2000 Study for FAO, and management of a large scale data collection on Agricultural Productivity and Market Transactions in Bihar and Punjab for the research department of The World Bank.

## **Cornell University**

1976-1977

Ithaca, NY
Research Associate

Worked on various research papers while preparing my thesis.

**Cornell University** 

1972-1974

Ithaca, NY

Research Assistant

Worked with John Mellor on another Two Sector Model, Analysis of Consumption data for India and my own paper on the relationship between the factor shares and elasticity of

substitution.

#### **Freelance Consultant**

1971-1972

Bombay, India

Worked on the mathematical side of a "Two-Sector Model Paper" and "The New Economics of Growth" book published by Mellor. Also worked on the analysis of an irrigation project for the Agricultural Finance Corporation.

#### **Gokhale Institute of Politics and Economics**

1983-1985

Pune, India Research Scholar

Econometric work and preparation on "240x240 Input-Output Table" for India.

#### **PUBLICATIONS/REPORTS:**

Between January 2002 and January 2018, over 100 letters related to Economic Development have been published in two magazines in India, namely, *Business Standard* and *Economic and Political Weekly*.

# Based on the above write ups I am planning to publish a book on economic growth in emerging market economies

#### The past publications are as follows:

- Ranade, C.G. "Hicks Coefficient to Depict Direction of Movements in Relative Factor Shares in Agricultural Production," <u>Southern Economic Journal</u>, April, 1977.
- Goldman, H.W. and C.G. Ranade, "Analysis of Income Effect on Food Consumption in Rural and Urban Philippines," <u>Journal of Agricultural Economics and Development</u>, vol.2, No.2, July 1977, pp. 150-165.
- Ranade, C.G. and R.W. Herdt, "Shares of Farm Earnings from Rice Production," in <u>Economic Consequences of the New Rice Technology</u> (ed. Randolph Barker and Yujiro Hayami), International Rice Research Institute, Manila, 1978, pp. 87-104.
- Ranade, C.G., "Impact of Technological Change on Intersectoral Flow of Resources," paper read at the International Conference of Agricultural Economists at Banff, Alberta, 1979.
- Ranade, C.G, R.B. Singh and K.H. Rao, <u>Marketing Channels and Price Spread in Cotton</u>, Centre for Management in Agriculture, Indian Institute of Management, 1979. (Book)

- Ranade, C.G., "Impact of Cropping Pattern on Agricultural Production," <u>Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics</u>, January-April 1981.
- Ranade, C.G., R.B. Singh and K.H. Rao, "Strategy for Stabilizing the Parity between Prices of Groundnut and Finished Manufactured Goods from Groundnut," <u>Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics</u>, vol.36, No. 4, October-December 1981, pp. 88-95.
- Ranade, C.G., "Rapporteur's Report on Slow Growth Crops Pulses, Oilseeds and Coarse Grains Technological, Economic and Environmental Constraints," <u>Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics</u>, vol. 37., No. 3, July-September 1982, pp. 417-420.
- Ranade, C.G., "Summary of Group Discussion on Slow Growth Crops Pulses, Oilseeds and Coarse Grains Technological, Economic and Environmental Constraints," <a href="Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics">Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics</a>, vol. 37, No. 4, October-December 1982, pp.461-161.
- Ranade, C.G., K.H. Rao and D.C. Sah, Groundnut Marketing in India, Centre for Management in Agriculture, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad, 1982. (Book)
- Ranade, C.G. and D.C. Sah, "Role of Cooperative and Private Trade Channels in Groundnut Marketing," <u>Commerce</u>, Annual Number on <u>Internal Trade of India</u>, 1982.
- Sah, D.C. and C.G. Ranade, "Bio-fertilizers in Indian Agriculture: A Case Study of Gujarat," Economic and Political Weekly (Review of Agriculture), April 1983.
- Ranade, C.G. and D.C. Sah, <u>Industrialized Utilization of Cotton Stalk: Problems and Prospects</u>, Center for Management in Agriculture, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad, December 1984.
- Ranade, C.G., D.P. Mathur, K. Ranganajan and V.K. Gupta. <u>Performance of Integrated Milk Cooperatives in India: A Study of Selected Cooperative Dairies in Gujarat and Maharashtra</u>, Centre for Management in Agriculture, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad, December 1984.
- Ranade, C.G., "Growth of Productivity in Indian Agriculture," Economic and Political Weekly, vol. XXI, Nos. 25 and 26, June 21-28, 1986
- Ranade, C.G.(with Christopher L. Delgado), "Technical Change and Agricultural Labor Use," <u>Accelerating Food Production Growth in Sub-Saharan Africa</u>, (ed. John W. Mellor, C.L. Delgado and M.J. Blackie), Johns Hopkins 1987.

- Mellor, John W. And C.G. Ranade, "Technological Change in a Low Labor Productivity, Land Surplus Economy: The African Development Problem," International Food Policy Research Institute, 1987 (unpublished theoretical two sector model paper).
- Ranade, C.G., "Agricultural Marketing and Pricing Policies in Malawi," paper prepared for MADIA, World Bank Workshop, January 21-27, 1987.
- Ranade, C.G. (with Sidi Jammeh), "Agricultural Pricing and Marketing in Senegal," paper prepared for MADIA, World Bank Workshop, January 21-27, 1987.
- Ranade, C.G. (and Sidi Jammeh), "Agricultural Development and Foreign Assistance: A Review of the World Bank's Experience in Senegal, 1969-1986," paper prepared for MADIA, March 25, 1987.
- World Bank 1988, <u>Redesign of Kaduna Agricultural Development Project</u>, Staff Appraisal (I led SAR team).
- Ranade, C.G., Dayanathan Jha and C. Delgado, "Technological Change, Production Costs and Supply Response, "<u>Agricultural Price Policies in Developing Countries</u> (ed. Rasruddin Ahmed and John Mellon), Johns Hopkins Press, 1988.
- World Bank 1989, <u>Sources of Growth in Nigerian Agriculture</u>, in the Sector Report, contributed a key chapter.
- World Bank 1990, Medium Team Agricultural Development Strategy for Ghana, in the Sector Report, contributed a key chapter.
- World Bank 1991, <u>Agricultural Sector Adjustment Credit for Ghana</u>, participated in the appraisal mission.
- World Bank 1992, <u>National Fadama Development Project for Nigeria</u>, (I led the SAR team from preparation until the Negotiations and Board Presentations).
- World Bank 1993, Agricultural Investment Project for Ghana, contributed to SAR.
- World Bank 1994, Contributed major chapter in the Financial Sector Review on Ghana on the subject of Rural Finance.
- Since 1994 I was involved in managing a large training program in Rural Development and Natural Resource Management explained at top.
- Mellor John and C. G. Ranade," The Effect of Agricultural Growth on Employment in Egypt: A Three-Sector Model," in **Does Agricultural Policy Reform Work?** (ed.) Gary Ender and John S. Holtzman, USAID-Abt Associates Inc. 2003.
- Mellor John and C. G. Ranade," How Does Agricultural Growth Dominate Poverty Reduction in Low and Middle Income Countries?" *Pakistan Development Review*, Spring 2007.

Ranade C. G. (2018), "Vertical Integration for Inclusive Growth in India", Presidential Address for Conference of the Indian Society of Agriculture Marketing, November 22, 2018, Bengaluru.

Ranade C. G. (2002 onwards), Since 2002, over 100 letters on the issues related to agriculture are published in the edited columns of the Economic and Political Weekly and the Business Standard, both from India.

Ranade C. G. (2019)," Future of Inclusive Growth in India," to published in a book in honor of R. Radhakrishna, "Springer, India

Ranade C. G. (2020): Seminar in Cornell on February 28, 2020 title," Role of Agriculture in Inclusive Development in India:,